<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nicholas Machiavel's letter to Zanobius Buondelmontius in vindication of himself and his writings..</title>
            <author>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186416</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2781:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nicholas Machiavel's letter to Zanobius Buondelmontius in vindication of himself and his writings..</title>
                  <author>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</author>
                  <author>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527.</author>
                  <author>Wharton, Thomas Wharton, Marquess of, 1648?-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and suggested approximate date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"The letter is supposititious; it was probably written by Henry Neville"--BM. Authorship sometimes but less probably attributed to Thomas Wharton.</note>
                  <note>Likely part of: Publisher or translator of Nicholas Machiavels whole works out of Italian, faithfully into English, concerning the following letter of Nicholas Machiavels, wherein he clears himself of the aspersions alledg'd by some on his writings.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:179237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>NICHOLAS MACHIAVEL'S LETTER TO ZANOBIUS BUONDELMONTIUS In VINDICATION of himſelf and his WRITINGS.</head>
            <p>THE Diſcourſe we had lately (dear <hi>Zenobio</hi>) in the delightful Gardens of our old deceaſed Friend <hi>Coſimo Rucellai,</hi> and the preſſing importunity of <hi>Guilio Silviati,</hi> that I would uſe ſome means to wipe off the many Aſperſions caſt upon my Writings, gives you the preſent trouble of reading this Letter, and me the pleaſure of writing it; which laſt would be infinitely greater, if I were not at this day too old, and too incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, and by the change of our Government wholly uncapable of performing, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my brain or my hand, any further ſervice to my Countrey; for it hath ever been my opinion, that whoſoever goes about to make men publickly acquainted with his actions, or apologize to the World for imputations laid upon him, cannot be excuſed from vanity and impertinence, except his parts and opportunities be ſuch, as may enable him to be inſtrumental for the good of others, and that he cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieve that excellent end, without juſtifying himſelf from having any indirect and baſe ones, and procuring truſt from men, by clearing the repute of his juſtice and integrity to them. But although this be far from my caſe; yet I have yeelded (you ſee) to the entreaty of <hi>Guilio</hi> and the reſt of that Company, not only becauſe I am ſufficiently (both by the reſtraint of our Preſs. and the diſcretion of the perſon I write to) aſſured that this Letter will never be made publick; but for that I eſteem it a Duty to clear that excellent Society, from the Scandal of having ſo dangerous and pernicious a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be a member of their converſation; for by reaſon of my Age, and ſince the loſs of our Liberty, and my ſufferings under that Monſter of luſt and cruelty <hi>Alexander de Medeci,</hi> ſet over us by the Divine vengeance for our ſins, I can be capable of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign or enjoyment, than to delight and be delighted in the company of ſo many choiſe and virtuous perſons, who now aſſemble themſelves with all ſecurity, under the happy and hopeful Reign of our new Prince, <hi>Coſimo;</hi> and we may ſay, that though our Common-wealth be not reſtored, our ſlavery is at an end, and that he coming in by our own choice, may prove (if I have as good skill in Propheſying as I have had formerlie) Anceſtor to many renowned Princes, who will govern this State in great quietneſs, and with great Clemencie; ſo that our Poſteritie is like to enjoy eaſe and ſecuritie, though not that greatneſs, wealth, and glorie, by which our City hath for ſome years paſt (even in the moſt factious and tumultuous times of our Democracie) given Law to <hi>Italy,</hi> and bridled the ambition of foreign Princes. But, that I may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179237:2"/>the Loquacitie incident to old men, I will come to the buſineſs. If I remember well, the exceptions that are taken to theſe poor things I have publiſhed, are reducible to three.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>That in all my Writings, I inſinuate my great affection to the Democratical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, even ſo much as to undervalue that of Monarchy in reſpect of it, which laſt I do, not obſcurely in many paſſages, teach, and as it were, perſwade the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to throw off.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Next, <hi>That in ſome places I vent very great impieties, ſlighting and vellifying the Church, as Author of all the miſgovernment in the World, and by ſuch contempt make way for Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And laſtly, <hi>That in my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ook of the Prince, I teach Monarchs all the execrable villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanies that can be invented, and inſtruct them how to break faith, and to oppreſs and enſlave their Subjects.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer ſomething to every one of theſe; and that I may obſerve a right me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, will begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>Having lived in an Age when our poor Countrie and Government have ſuffered more changes and revolutions, than ever did perhaps befall any people in ſo ſhort a time, and having had till the taking of <hi>Florence,</hi> may ſhare in the managing of affairs, during almoſt all theſe alterations; ſometimes in the qualitie of <hi>Secretary</hi> of our City, and ſometimes employed in <hi>Embaſſages</hi> abroad, I ſet my ſelf to read the Hiſtorie of Ancient and Modern times, that I might by that means find out whether there had not been in all Ages the like viciſſitudes and accidents in State affairs, and to ſearch out the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them, and having in ſome ſort ſatisfied my ſelf therein, I could not abſtain from ſcribling ſomething of the two chief kinds of Government, <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy;</hi> of which all other formes are but mixtures, and ſince neither my Parts nor Learning could arrive to follow the ſteps of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> by writing according to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Art, as <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> and many others have done upon this ſubject; I did content my ſelf to make ſlight obſervations upon both; by giving a bare character of a <hi>Prince,</hi> as to the <hi>Monarchical</hi> frame, and as to the Popular chuſing the perfecteſt and moſt ſucceſsful of all Governments of that kind upon Earth, and in my Diſcourſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, following the order of my Author, without ever taking upon me to argue proble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticallie, much leſs to dicide which of theſe two Governments is the beſt: if from my way of handling matters in my diſcourſes upon <hi>Livy,</hi> and from thoſe incomparable Virtues, and great Actions we read of in that <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and from the obſervations I make, men will conclude (which is, I muſt confeſs my opinion) that the excellencie of thoſe Counſels and Atchievements, and the improvement which Mankind, and as I may ſo ſay, Humane Nature it ſelf obtained amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> did proceed natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally from their Government; and was but a plain effect and conſequence of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their Common-wealth: I ſay if Readers will thus judge, how can I in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be accuſed for that; it would become thoſe who lay this blame upon me to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them whom my Papers have miſled, and to ſhew the World to what other cauſes we may impute thoſe admirable effects, thoſe Heroick qualities and performances, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and purity of manners, that ſcorning of riches and life it ſelf, when the publick was concerned: If they pleaſe to do this, they will oblidge my Readers, who will owe to ſuch the rectifying their Judgements, and not at all offend me, who have reaſoned this matter impartially and without paſſion; nor have poſſitively affirmed any thing. But, what if this part of my accuſation had been true? Why ſhould I be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179237:2"/>of Hereſie, or indiſcretion of preferring a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> before a <hi>Monarchy?</hi> Was I not Born, Bred, and imployed in a City, which being at the time I write, under that form of Government, did owe all wealth and greatneſs, and all proſperity to it? If I had not very deſignedly avoided all dogmaticalneſs in my obſervations (being not willing to imitate young Scholars in their Declamations) I might eaſily have concluded from the premiſſes I lay down, that a <hi>Democracy</hi> founded upon good orders is the beſt and moſt excellent Government, and this without the leaſt fear of confutation; for I firmly believe, that there are none but Flatterers and Sophiſters would oppoſe me, ſuch as will reſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and even <hi>Plato</hi> himſelf, to make them write for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> by miſapplying ſome looſe paſſages in thoſe great Authors; nay, will tell their Readers, that what is moſt like the Government of the World by GOD is the beſt, which wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon his abſolute Power; to make this compariſon, run with four feet, theſe Sycophants muſt give the poor Prince they intend to Diefie, a better and ſuperior Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Humanity, muſt Creat a neceſſary dependance of all Creatures upon him, muſt endue him with infinite wiſdom and goodneſs, and even with Omnipotency it ſelf. It will be hard for any man to be miſled in this Argument by proofs wreſted from <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> ſince whoſoever reads attentively the Hiſtorical part of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> ſhall find that GOD himſelf never made but one Government for men, that this Government was a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> (wherein the <hi>Sanchadrim</hi> or <hi>Senate,</hi> and the Congregation or <hi>popular Aſſembly</hi> had their ſhare) and that he manifeſted his high diſpleaſure when the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people would turn it into a <hi>Monarchy;</hi> but that I may not ſtricke upon the rock I profeſs to ſhun, I ſhall paſs to that which is fit indeed to be wip'd off, and which if it were true, would not only juſtly expoſe me to the hatred and vengeance of GOD, and all good men, but even deſtroy the deſign and purpoſe of all my Writings, which is to treat in ſome ſort (as well as one of my ſmall parts can hope to do) of the <hi>Politicks.</hi> And how can any man pretend to write concerning <hi>Policy,</hi> who deſtroyes the moſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential part of it, which is obedience to all Governments. It will be very eaſie then for <hi>Guilio Salviati,</hi> or any other member of our Society, to believe the Proteſtation I make, that the animating of private men either directly or indirectly to diſobey, much leſs to ſhake off, any government how diſpotical ſoever, was never in my Thoughts or Writings; thoſe who are unwilling to give credit to this, may take the pains to aſſign in any of my Books, the paſſages they imagine to tend that way, (for I can think of none my ſelf) that ſo I may give ſuch perſons more particular ſatisfaction; I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have a diſcourſe in one of my Books, to encourage the <hi>Italian</hi> Nation, to aſſume their ancient valour, and to expel the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> meaning (as the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> uſed the word) all Strangers from amongſt us; but that was before the <hi>Kings of Spain</hi> had quiet poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> or the <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Milan;</hi> ſo that I could not be interpreted to mean that the people of thoſe two Dominions ſhould be ſtir'd up to ſhake off their Princes, becauſe they were Forreigners, ſince at that time <hi>Lodovie Sforza</hi> was in poſſeſſion of the one, and K. <hi>Frederick</hi> reſtored to the other, both <hi>Natives</hi> of <hi>Italy;</hi> but my deſign was to exhort our Countrey-men not to ſuffer this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince</hi> to be the Scene of the Arms and ambition of <hi>Charles</hi> the 8th. or K. <hi>Lewis</hi> his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour who when they had a mind to renew the old Title of the Houſe of <hi>Anjou</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> came with ſuch force into <hi>Italy,</hi> that not only our goods were plundered, and our Lands waſted, but even the liberty of our Cities and Governments endangered, but to unite and oppoſe them, and to keep this <hi>Province</hi> in the hands of <hi>Princes</hi> of our own Nation, this my intention is ſo viſible in the Chapter it ſelf, that I need but refer you to it. Yet that I may not anſwer this imputation barely by denying, I ſhall aſſert in this place what my principles are in that which the World calls <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which I believe to be not only riſing in Arms againſt any government we live under, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179237:3"/>to acknowledge that word to extend to all <hi>clandeſtine Conſpiracies</hi> too, by which the peace and quiet of any Countrey may be interrupted, and by conſequence the Lives and Eſtates of innocent Perſons endangered. <hi>Rebellion</hi> then ſo deſcribed, I hold to be the greateſt crime that can be committed amongſt men, both againſt Policy, Morality, and <hi>in foro Conſcientiae;</hi> but notwithſtanding all this, it is an offence which will be commited whilſt the World laſts, as often as Princes tyrannize, and by enſlaving and oppreſſing their Subjects, make Magiſtracy, which was intended for the benefit of Mankind, prove a Plague and Deſtruction to it; for let the terrour and the guilt be never ſo great, it is impoſſible that Humane Nature, which conſiſts of Paſſion as well as Virtue can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with patience and ſubmiſſion the greateſt cruelty and injuſtice, when ever either the weakneſs of their Princes, the unamity of the People, or any other favourable accident, ſhall give them reaſonable hopes to mend their condition, and provide better for their own intereſt by inſurrection. So that Princes and States ought in the Conduct of their Affairs, not only to conſider what their people are bound to ſubmit to; if they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired from Heaven, or were all Moral Philoſophers; but to weigh likewiſe what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable <hi>de facto</hi> to fall out, in this corrupt age of the World, and to reflect upon thoſe dangerous Tumults, which have happened frequently not only upon oppreſſion, but even by reaſon of Malverſation, and how ſome <hi>Monarchies</hi> have been wholly ſubverted and changed into <hi>Democracies</hi> by the Tyranny of Princes; as we ſee (to ſay nothing of <hi>Rome</hi>) the powerful <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Swiſſerland</hi> brought by that means a little before the laſt age, to a conſiderable <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> courted and ſought to by all the <hi>Potentats</hi> in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi> If Princes will ſeriouſly conſider this matter, I make no queſtion but they will Rule with Clemency and Moderation, and return to that excellent Maxim of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients (almoſt exploded in this Age) that the intereſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> and of their People is the ſame, which truth it hath been the whole deſin of my Writings to convince them of.</p>
            <p>I am charged then, in the ſecond place, with <hi>impiety, and villifying the Church, and ſo to make way for Atheiſm.</hi> I do not deny but that I have very frequently in my Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, laid the blame upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not only for all the miſgovernment of Chriſtendom; but even for the depravation and almoſt total deſtruction of <hi>Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> it ſelf in this Province; but that this diſcourſe of mine doth, or can tend to teach men impiety; or to make way for Atheiſm, I preremptorily deny: and although for proof of my innocence herein., I need but refer you and all others to my Papers themſelves, as they are now publiſhed (where you will find all my reaſons drawn from experience, and frequent examples cited, which is ever my way of arguing) yet ſince I am put upon it, I ſhall in a few lines make that matter poſſibly a little clearer; and ſhall firſt make prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, That as I do undoubtedly hope, by the Merits of CHRIST, and by Faith in Him, to attain Eternal Salvation; ſo I do firmly believe the Chriſtian Profeſſion to be the only true Religion now in the World: Next, I am fully perſwaded, that all Divine Verities, which GOD then deſigned to teach the World, are contained in the Books of holy Scripture, as they are now extant and received amongſt us. From them I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that GOD created Man in purity and innocence, and that the firſt of that Species, by their frailty, loſt at once their integrity and their Paradiſe, and intail'd ſin and miſery upon their Poſterity; that Almighty GOD to repair this loſs, did out of his infinite Mercy, and with unparallel'd grace and goodneſs, ſend his only begotten Son into the World, to teach us new truths, to be a perfect example of virtue, goodneſs, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to reſtore true Religion, degenerated amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> into Superſtition, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and Hypocriſie, to die for the Salvation of Mankind; and in fine, to give to us the holy Spirit, to regenerate our Hearts, ſupport our Faith, and lead us into all truth. Now If it ſhall appear, that as the luſts of our firſt Parents did at that time diſappoint the good intention of GOD, in making a pure World, and brought in by their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179237:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the corruptions that are now in it. So that ſince likewiſe the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> by their inſatiable ambition and avarice, have deſignedly, as much as in them lies, fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the merciful purpoſe he had, in the happy Reſtauration He intended the World by his Son, and in the renewing and reforming of Humane Nature, and have wholly defaced and ſpoil'd Chriſtian Religion, and made it a Worldly and a Heatheniſh thing; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together uncapable, as it is practiſed amongſt them, either of directing the wayes of its Profeſſors to virtue and good life, or of ſaving their Souls hereafter. If, I ſay, this do appear I know no reaſon why I, for detecting thus much, and for giving warning to the World to take heed of their wayes, ſhould be accuſed of Impiety or Atheiſm; or why his Holineſs ſhould be ſo inraged againſt the poor Inhabitants of the Valleys in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Albigeſi</hi> for calling him Antichriſt: but to find that it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, I mean that the <hi>Popes</hi> have corrupted Chriſtian Religion, we need but read the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> (acknowledged by themſelves to be of infallible truth) and there we ſhall ſee, that the Faith and Religion preached by Chriſt, and ſetled afterwards by his Apoſtles, and cultivated by their Sacred Epiſtles, is ſo different a thing from the Chirſtianity that is now profeſs'd and taught at <hi>Rome,</hi> that we ſhould be convinc'd, that if thoſe Holy Men ſhould be ſent by GOD again into the World, they would take more pains to confute this <hi>Gallimufry,</hi> than ever they did to preach down the Tradition of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> or the Fables and Idolatry of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and would in probability ſuffer a new Martyrdom in that City under the Vicar of CHRIST, for the ſame Doctrine which once animated the Heathen Tyrants againſt them. Nay, we have ſomething more to ſay againſt theſe Sacrilegious pretenders to GODS power; for whereas all other falſe worſhips have been ſet up by ſome politick Legiſlators, for the ſupport and preſervation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, this falſe, this ſpurious Religion brought in upon the ruines of Chriſtianity by the <hi>Popes,</hi> hath deformed the face of Government in <hi>Europe;</hi> deſtroying all the good principles, and Morality left us by the Heathen themſelves; and introduced in ſtead thereof, Sordid, Cowardly, and impolitick Notions, whereby they have ſubjected Mankind, and even great <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> to their own <hi>Empire,</hi> and never ſuffered any Orders or Maxims to take place where they have power, that might make a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wiſe, Honeſt, Great or Wealthy: This I have ſet down ſo plainly in thoſe paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of my Book which are complained of, that I ſhall ſay nothing at all for the proof of it in this place, but refer you thither, and come to ſpeak a little more particularly of my firſt aſſertion; that the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Clergy</hi> have deſtroyed Chriſtian Religion. Upon this ſubject I could infinitely wiſh, new Letters begin to revive again, that ſome Learned Pen would employ it ſelf, and that ſome perſon verſ'd in the Chronoligy of the Church (as they call it) would deduce out of the Eccleſiaſtical Writers, the time and manner how theſe abuſes crept in; and by what Arts and Steps this <hi>Babel</hi> that reaches at Heaven, was built by theſe Sons of the Earth; but this matter as unſuitable to the brevity of a Letter, and indeed more to my ſmall Parts and Learning, I ſhall not pretend to, being one who never hitherto ſtudied or write of Theology, further than it did naturally concern he <hi>Politicks;</hi> therefore I ſhall only deal by the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as I have done formerly by <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> that is, make obſervations or reflections upon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and leave you and Mr. <hi>Guilio,</hi> and the reſt of our Society to make the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not citing like Preache's, the Chapter or Verſe; becauſe the reading of Holy Scripture is little uſ'd, and indeed hardly permitted amongſt us. To begin at the top, I would have any reaſonable man tell me, whence this unmeaſurable power, long claim'd, and now poſſeſſ'd by the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> is derived, firſt of being CHRISTS Vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar, and by that (as I may ſo ſay) pretending to a Monopoly of the Holy Spirit (which was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and given to the whole Church, that is, to the Elect or Saints) as is plain by a cl<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Serinon, made the very ſame time that the miraculous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179237:4"/>gifts of the Spirit of GOD were firſt given to the Apoſtles, who ſayes to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Repent and be Baptized every one of you in the name of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>for the remiſſion of ſins, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, for this promiſe is to you and your Children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the LORD our GOD ſhall call.</hi> Next, to judge infallibly of Divine Truth, and to forgive ſins as CHRIST did. Then to be the Head of all Eccleſiaſtical Perſons and Cauſes in the World; to be ſo far above <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> as to Judge, Depoſe, and Deprive them, and to have an abſolute Juriſdiction over all the affairs in Chriſtendom, <hi>in Ordine ad Spiritualia;</hi> yet all this the Canoniſts allow him, and he makes no ſcruple to aſſume, whilſt it is plain that in the whole <hi>New Teſtament</hi> there is no deſcription made of ſuch an Officer to be at any time in the Church, except it be in the Prophecy of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> or in one of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, where he ſayes, <hi>Who it is that ſhall ſit in the Temple of GOD, ſhewing himſelf that he is GOD.</hi> CHRIST tells us, <hi>his Kingdom is not of this World;</hi> And, <hi>if any will be the greateſt amongſt his Diſciples, that he muſt be ſervant to the reſt,</hi> which ſhews that his Followers were to be great in Sanctity and Humility, and not in worldly power.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writting to the Chriſtians of thoſe times, almoſt in every Epiſtle commands them <hi>to be obedient to the Higher Powers. or Magiſtrates ſet over them;</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf (from whom this extravagant Empire is pretended to be derived) in his firſt Epiſtle, bids us <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every ordinance of man for the LORDS ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the King, or, &amp;c.</hi> and this is enjoyn'd although it is plain, that they who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd the World in thoſe days, were both Heathens, Tyrants, and Uſurpers, and in this ſubmiſſion there is no exception or <hi>proviſo</hi> for Eccleſiaſtical immunity The pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice as well as precepts of thoſe Holy Men ſhews plainly that they had no intention to leave Succeſſors, who ſhould deprive Hereditary Princes from their right of Reigning for differing in Religion, who without all doubt are by the appointment of the Apoſtle, and by the principles of Chriſtianity, to be obeyed and ſubmitted to (in things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the fundamental Laws of the Government give them power) though they were <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles.</hi> If I ſhould tell you by what Texts in Scripture the <hi>Popes</hi> claim the powers before mentioned, it would ſtir up your laughter, and prove too light for ſo ſerious a matter; yet becauſe poſſibly you have never heard ſo much of this ſubject before, I ſhall inſtance in a few: They tell you therefore that the Juriſdiction they pretend over the Church, and the power of pardoning ſins, comes from CHRIST to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and from him to them. <hi>Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock I will build my Church, I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, &amp;c.</hi> From theſe two Texts ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly applyed, comes this great Tree which hath with its branches over-ſpread the whole Earth, and kill'd all the good and wholſome Plants growing upon it; The firſt Text will never by any man of ſence be underſtood to ſay more, than that the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Suffering, and Miniſtry of <hi>Peter,</hi> was like to be a great foundation and Pillar of the Doctrine of Chriſt; the other Text (as alſo another ſpoken by our Saviour, to all his Apoſtles, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit they are remitted, and whoſe ſins ye retain they are retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>) are all by the primitive Fathers interpreted in this manner, whereſoever you ſhall effectually preach the Goſpel, you ſhall carry with you Grace, and Remiſſion of ſins to them which ſhall follow your inſtructions; but the people who ſhal not have theſe joyful Tidings communicated by you to them, ſhall remain in darkneſs, and in their ſins. But if any will conteſt, that by ſome of theſe laſt Texts, that Evangelical Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was afterwards brought into the Church by the Apoſtles, was here praeſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by our great Maſter, how unlike were thoſe cenſures to thoſe now thundered out (as he calls it) by the <hi>Pope?</hi> theſe were for edification, and not deſtruction, to afflict the fleſh for the ſalvation of the Soul; that the Apoſtolical Ordinance was pronounced
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179237:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>for ſome notorious Scandal or Apoſtacy from the Faith, and firſt decreed by the Church; that is, the whole Congregation preſent, and then denounced by the Paſtor, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only to debar ſuch perſons from partaking of the Communion or fellowſhip of that Church, till Repentance ſhould re-admit him, but was followed by no other proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or chaſtiſement, as is now practiſed. But ſuppoſe all theſe Texts had been as they would have them, how does this make for the Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter</hi> or the reſt? Or how can this prove the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> to have right to ſuch Succeſſion? But I make haſte from this ſubject, and ſhal urge but one Text more; which is, <hi>the ſpiritual man judgeth all men, but is himſelf judged of none;</hi> from whence is inferred by the Canoniſts, that firſt, the Pope is the Spiritual man; and then that he is to be Judge of all the World; and laſt, that he is never to belyable to any judgment himſelf; whereas it is obvious to the meaneſt underſtanding: St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this text means to diſtinguiſh between a perſon inſpired with the Spirit of God, and one remaining in the ſtate of Nature, which latter he ſayes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not judge of thoſe Heavenly gifts and graces, as he explains himſelf when he ſayes, <hi>The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man cannot diſcern the things of the Spirit, becauſe they are fooliſhneſs unto him.</hi> To take my leave of this matter wholly out of the way of my Studies, I ſhall beg of you <hi>Zenobio</hi> and of <hi>Guilio,</hi> and the reſt of our Society to read over carefully the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and then to ſee what ground there is for Purgatory (by which all the wealth and greatneſs hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew'd to theſe men) what colour for the Idolatrous worſhip of Saints, and their Images, and particularly for ſpeaking in their hymes and prayers to a peice of wood (the Croſs Imean) <hi>Salve Lignum,</hi> &amp;c. and then <hi>fac nos dignos beneficiorum Chriſti,</hi> as you may read in that Office, what colour, or rather what excuſe for that horrid unchriſtian, and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Engine called the <hi>inquiſition,</hi> brought in by the command and authority of the <hi>Pope,</hi> the inventor of which, <hi>Peter</hi> a Dominican Fryer having been ſlain amongſt the <hi>Albigeſi,</hi> as he well deſerved, is now Cannoniz'd for a Saint, and ſtil'd, <hi>San Pietro Martine:</hi> In the dreadfull Priſons of this Inquiſition, many faithfull and pious Chriſtians (to ſay nothing of honeſt Moral <hi>Moors</hi> or <hi>Mahometans</hi>) are tormented and famiſh'd, or, if they out-live their ſufferings burnt quickly to death, and that only for differing in Religion from the <hi>Pope,</hi> without having any crime, or the leaſt miſdemeanor proved or alledged againſt them, and this is inflicted upon theſe poor Creatures, by thoſe who profeſs to believe the Scripture, which tells us, that <hi>faith is the gift of God,</hi> without whoſe ſpeciall illumination no man can obtain it; and therefore is not in reaſon or humanity to be puniſhed for wanting it: And Chriſt himſelf hath ſo clearly decided that point in bidding us let the tares and the wheat grow together till the Harveſt, that I ſhall never make any difficulty to call him Antichriſt, who ſhall uſe the leaſt perſecution whatſoever agianſt any differing in matters of faith from himſelf, whether the perſon ſo diſſenting, be <hi>Heretick, Jew, Gentile,</hi> or <hi>Mahometan:</hi> Next, I beſeech you to obſerve in reading that Holy Book (though Chriſtian faſts are doubtleſs of Divine right) what ground there is for enjoying fiſh to be eaten (at leaſt fleſh to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from) for one third part of the year, by which they put the poor to great hardſhip, who not having purſes to buy wholſom fiſh, are ſubjected to all the miſeries and diſeaſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to a bad and unhealthful dyet, whilſt the rich, and chiefly themſelves and their <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals,</hi> exceed <hi>Lucullus</hi> in their Luxury, of <hi>Oyſters, Turbats, tender Crabs,</hi> and <hi>Carpioni</hi> brought ſome hundreds of miles to feed their gluttony, upon theſe penetential days of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from <hi>Beeff</hi> and <hi>Pork.</hi> It may be it will lye in the way of thoſe who obſerve this, to enquire what St. <hi>Paul</hi> means when he ſays, <hi>That in the latter days ſome ſhall depart from the faith, forbidding to marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats which God hath created to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with thankſgiving;</hi> but all theſe things, and many other abuſes brought in by theſe Perverters of Chriſtianity, will I hope e're long be enquired into by ſome of the Diſciples of that bold Fryer, who the very ſame year in which I profecied that the ſcourge of the Church was not far off, began to thunder againſt their Indulgencies, and ſince hath queſtioned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179237:5"/>many tenets long received and impoſed upon the world. I ſhal conclude this diſcourſe after I have ſaid a word of the moſt Helliſh of all the innovations brought in by the <hi>Popes,</hi> which is the Clergy; theſe are a ſort of men under pretence of miniſtring to the people in holy things, ſet a part and ſeparated from the reſt of mankind (from whom they have a very diſtinct, and a very oppoſite intereſt) by a humane Ceremony called by a divine name, <hi>viz.</hi> Ordination, theſe wherever they are found (with the whole body of the Monks and Fryers, who are called the regular Clargy) make a Band which may be called the <hi>Janizaries of the Papacy;</hi> theſe have been the cauſers of all the Soloeciſms and immortalities in Government, and of all the impieties and abominations in Religion, and by conſequence of all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, villany, and corruption we ſuffer under in this deteſtable Age; theſe men by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome's</hi> help, have crept into all the Governments in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> where there is any mixture of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and made themſelves a third eſtate; that is, have, by their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities (which are almoſt a third part of all the Lands in <hi>Europe</hi> given them by the blind zeal, or rather folly of the <hi>Northern</hi> people, who over-ran this part of the world) ſtept into the throne, and what they cannot perform by theſe ſecular helps, and by the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy their vaſſals have upon them, they fail not to claim and to uſurp, by the power they pretend to have from God and his Vicegerent at <hi>Rome.</hi> They exempt themſelves, their Lands and Goods, from all ſecular juriſdiction; that is, from all Courts of Juſtice and Magiſtracy, and will be Judges in their own Cauſes, as in matters of tithe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not content with this, will appoint Courts of their own to decide Soveraignly in teſtamentary matters, and many other cauſes; and take upon them to be ſole Puniſhers of many great Crimes, as Witchcraft, Sorcery, Adultery, and all uncleanneſs; to ſay nothing of the fore-mentioned judicatory of the Inquiſition: in theſe laſt caſes they turn the offenders over to be puniſh'd (when they have given Sentence) by the ſecular arm, ſo they call the Magiſtrate, who is blindly to execute their decrees under pain of Hell-fire; as if Chriſtian Princes and Governours were appointed only by God to be their Bravo's or Hangmen. They give Protection and Sanctuary, to all execrable offenders, even to Murderers themſelves, (whom God commanded to be indiſpenſably puniſh'd with death) if they come within their Churches, Cloyſters, or any other place, which they will pleaſe to call holy ground; and if the ordinary juſtice, nay, the Soveraign power, do proceed againſt ſuch offenders, they thunder out their Excommunication; that is, cut off from the body of Chriſt, not the Prince only, but the whole Nation and People, ſhutting the Church doors, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divine offices to ceaſe, and ſometimes even authorizing the people to riſe up in Arms, and conſtrain their Governours to a ſubmiſſion, as happened to this poor City in the time of our Anceſtors, when for but forbidding the ſervant of a poor Carmelite Fryer (who had vowed poverty, and ſhould have kept none) to go arm'd, and puniſhing his diſobedience with impriſonment, our whole Senate with their <hi>Gonfalonier</hi> were conſtrained to go to <hi>Avignon</hi> for abſolution, and in caſe of refuſal, had been maſſacred by the people. It would almoſt aſtoniſh a wiſe man to imagine how theſe folks ſhould acquire an Empire ſo diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Chriſtian religion, and ſo pernicious to the intereſts of men, but it will not ſeem ſo miraculous to them who ſhall ſeriouſly conſider, that the Clergy hath been more than theſe thouſand years upon the catch, and a form'd united corporation againſt the purity of Religion, and the intereſt of mankind, and have not only wreſted the Holy Scripture to their own advantage (which they have kept from the Laity in unknown languages, and by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the reading thereof) but made uſe likewiſe firſt of the blind devotion and ignorance of the <hi>Goths, Vandls, Huns,</hi> &amp;c. and ſince of the ambition and avarice of Chriſtian Princes, ſtirring them up one againſt another, and ſending them upon fooliſh errands to the Holy Land, to loſe their Lives, and to leave their Dominions, in the mean time, expoſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Complices. They have beſides kept Learning and Knowledge among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſtiffling the light of the Goſpel, crying down Moral vertues as ſplendid ſins, defac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179237:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>humane policy, deſtroying the purity of the Chriſtian faith and profeſſion, and all that was vertuous, prudent, regular and orderly upon earth; ſo that whoever would do good, and good men ſervice, get himſelf immortal honour in this life, and eternal glory in the next, would reſtore the good police (I had almoſt ſaid with my Author <hi>Livy</hi> the ſanctuary too) of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> with all their valour, and other glorious endowments; I ſay, whoever would do this, muſt make himſelf powerfull enough to extirpate this curſed and apoſtate race out of the world, and that you may ſee this is lawfull as well as neceſſary, I ſhall ſay but one word of their calling and original, and then leave this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. The word Clergy is a term, wholly unknown to the Scriptures, otherwiſe than in this ſence; a peculiar People or Gods lot, uſed often for the whole Jewiſh Nation, who are likewiſe called a Kingdom of Prieſts in ſome places. In the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> the word <hi>Cleros</hi> is taken for the true Believers, who are alſo called the Elect, and often the Church, which is the Aſſembly of the faithful met together, as is eaſily ſeen by reading the beginning of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, where writting to the Church of Churches, he uſually explains himſelf, <hi>To all the Saints in Chriſt;</hi> ſometimes, <hi>To all who have obtained like faith with us;</hi> ſometimes, <hi>To all who in all places call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. by which it appears, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the word Church nor Clergy was in thoſe dayes ever appropriated to the Paſtors or Elders of the flock; but did ſignifie indifferently all the people aſſembled together; which is likewiſe the literal conſtruction of the word <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> which is an aſſembly or meeting; in theſe Congregations of Churches was performed their Ordination, which properly ſignifies no more than a decree of ſuch Aſſembly; but is particularly uſed for an Election of any into the Miniſtry. The manner was this, ſometimes the Apoſtles themſelves in their Perigrina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſometimes any other eminent Member of the Church, did propoſe to the Society (upon vacancy, or other neceſſity of a Paſtor, Elder, or Deacon) ſome good Holy man to be Elected, which perſon if he had parts or gifts, ſuch as the Church could edifie by, was choſen by the lifting up of hands, that is by ſuffrage, and oftentimes hands were laid u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, and Prayer made for him. Theſe men ſo ſet apart did not pretend to any conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, or ſacredneſs more than they had before, much leſs to become a diſtinct thing from the reſt of mankind, as if they had been metemorphos'd, but did attend to perform the ſeveral functions of their calling, as prophecying; that is, Preaching the Goſpel, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and never intermitted the ordinary buſineſs of their Trade or Profeſſion, unleſs their Church or Congregation was very numerous, in which caſe they were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by alms or contribution, which was laid aſide by every member, and collected the firſt day of the week by the Deacons, this was ſaid to be given the Church, and was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by ſuffrage of the whole Collective Body to the poor, and to other incidencies, ſo far was it from Sacriledge in thoſe days to employ Church goods to Layuſes. From theſe words, <hi>Church, Clergy, Ordination, Paſtor,</hi> (which laſt hath been tranſlated of late years <hi>Biſhop</hi>) you ſee what concluſions theſe men have deduced, and how immenſe a ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture they have raiſed, upon ſo little a foundation, and how eaſily it will fall to the ground, when GOD ſhall inſpire Chriſtian Princes and States to redeem his truths, and his poor enſlaved Members out of their clutches, to bring back again into the World, the true Original Chriſtian Faith, with the Apoſtolical Churches, Paſtors, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo conſiſtent with Moral virtue and integrity, ſo helpful and conducing to the beſt and moſt prudent Policy, ſo fitted for Obedience to Magiſtracy and Government, all which the World hath for many years been deprived of, by the execrable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ill quality, which is inſeparable from Prieſt-craft, and the conjuration or ſpell of their new invented Ordination; by which they cry with the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Jam furor humanum noſtro de pectore ſenſum</l>
                  <l>Expulit &amp; totum ſpirant praecordia Phoebum.</l>
               </q> which makes them ſo Sacred, and Holy, that they have nothing of integrity, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179237:6"/>of Humanity left in them. I hope I ſhall not be thought impious any longer, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this point, I mean for vindicating Chriſtian Religion from the aſſaults of theſe men, who having the confidence to believe, or at leaſt profeſs themſelves the only inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which GOD hath choſen or can chooſe to teach and reform the World (though they have neither Moral virtues, or Natural parts equal to other men for the moſt part) have by this pretence prevail'd ſo far upon the common ſort of people, and upon ſome too of a better quality, that they are perſwaded their Salvation or Eternal Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depends upon believing or not believing of what they ſay. I would not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, to diſſwade any from honoring the true Apoſtolical Teachers, when they ſhall be re-eſtabliſhed amongſt us, or from allowing them (even of right, and not of alms or curteſie) ſuch Emoluments as may enable them cheerfully to perform the duties of their charge, to provide for their Children, and even to uſe Hoſpitality as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> But this I will propheſie before I conclude, that if Princes ſhall perform this buſineſs by halves, and leave any root of this Clergy or Prieſt-craft, as it now is, in the ground; or if that famous Reformer, fled ſome years ſince out of <hi>Picardy</hi> to <hi>Geneva,</hi> who is of ſo great renown for learning and parts, and who promiſes us ſo perfect a reformation, ſhall not in his model wholly extirpate this ſort of men, then I ſay I muſt foretel, that as well the Magiſtrate as this Workman, will find themſelves deceived in their expectation, and that the leaſt <hi>fibra</hi> of this plant will over-run again the whole Vineyard of the Lord, and turn to a diffuſive Papacy in every Dioceſs, perhaps in every Pariſh: So that God in his mercy inſpire them to cut out the core of the Ulcer, and the bag of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, that it may never rankle or feſter any more, nor break out hereafter, to diffuſive new corruption and putrifaction through the body of Chriſt, which is his Holy Church, nor to vitiate and infect the good order and true policy of Government.</p>
            <p>I come now to the laſt branch of my charge, which is, <hi>That I teach Princes villany, and how to enſlave and oppreſs their Subjects,</hi> In which accuſation I am dealt with as poor <hi>Agnollo Canini</hi> was, who, as they report, being a very learned Practiſer of the Laws, and left the only man of this profeſſion (one Autumn) in our City, the reſt of the Advocates being fled into the countrey for fear of a contagious Diſeaſe which then reigned, was commanded by our Judges to aſſiſt with his counſel both parties, and to draw Pleas as well for the Defendant as the Plantiff, elſe the Courts of Juſtice muſt have been ſhut up. In the ſame manner my accuſers handle me, and make me firſt exhort and teach Subjects to throw off their Princes, and then to inſtruct Monarchs how to enſlave and oppreſs them; but I did not expect ſuch ingratitude from mine own Citizens, or to be ſerved as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, when he was upbraided for killing the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> by one of his own people for whoſe ſake he had done it, whereas he believed they would have underſtood by that action, that he was the perſon whom God intended to make uſe of in delivering them from the horrid ſlavery they were then under. If any man will read over my Book of the Prince with impartiality and ordinary charity, he will eaſily perceive, that it is not my intention therein to recommend that Government, or thoſe men there diſcribed, to the world; much leſs to teach them to trample upon good men, and all that is Sacred and Venerable upon earth, Laws, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Honeſty, and what not; if I have been a little too punctual in deſigning theſe Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and drawn them to the life in all their lineaments and colours, I hope mankind will know them the better to avoid them, my Treatiſe being both a Satyr againſt them, and a true Character of them: I ſpeak nothing of great and honourable Princes, as the Kings of <hi>England, France,</hi> and others; who have the States and Orders of their Kingdoms with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Laws, and Conſtitution, to found and maintain their Government; and who reign over the hearts as well as the perſons of their ſubjects; I treat only of thoſe vermin bred out of the corruption of our own ſmall Common-wealths and Cities, or engender'd by the ill blaſts that come from <hi>Rome, Olivaretto da Fermo, Borgia, the Baglioni,</hi> the <hi>Bentivoglii,</hi> and a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179237:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>hundred others; who having had neither right nor honorable means to bring them to their power, uſe it with more violence, rapine, and cruelty upon the poor people, than thoſe other renowned Princes ſhew to the Boars, the Wolves, the Foxes, and other ſavage beaſts which are the objects of their chaſe and hunting: whoſoever in his Empire over men is ty'd to no other rules than thoſe of his own will and luſt, muſt either be a Saint to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his paſſions, or elſe a very Devil incarnate; or if he be neither of theſe, both his life and reign are like to be very ſhort; for whoſoever takes upon him ſo execrable an employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to rule men againſt the Laws of nature and of reaſon, muſt turn all topſie turvy, and never ſtick at any thing, for if once he halt, he will fall and never riſe again: I hope after this I need ſay little to juſtifie my ſelf from the calumny of adviſing theſe Monſters to break their faith, ſince to keep it is to loſe their Empire, faithfulneſs and ſincerity being their mortal enemies, an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gucceone della Faggivola</hi> to one who upbraided him, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver employed honeſt men; anſwered, <hi>Honeſt men will cut my throat, let the King uſe honeſt men,</hi> meaning the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> who was eſtabliſhed in his Throne, and had right to it. But that I may have occaſion to juſtifie my ſelf againſt a little more then I am accuſed of, I will confeſs, that in a work where AI deſired to be a little more ſerious, than I was in this Book of the Prince, I did affirm, that in what way ſoever men defended their Country, whether by breaking or keeping their faith, it was ever well defended, not meaning in a ſtrick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſence, or point of honour, but explaining my ſelf that <hi>de facto</hi> the infamy of the breach of word, would quickly be forgotten and pardoned by the world, which is very true. Nay, what if I had ſaid that good ſucceſs in any interprize A(a far leſs conſideration than piety to our Country) would have cancell'd the bleame of ſuch perfidy as <hi>Caeſar</hi> (whom I compare to <hi>Cataline</hi>) us'd towards his fellow-Citizen, not only nor deteſted by poſterity, but even crown'd with renown and immortal fame; inſomuch as Princes to this day (as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved elſewhere) think it an honour to be compared to him, and the higheſt pitch of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration their flatterers can arrive at, is to call them by the names of one who violated his faith, and enſlav'd his Country. I hope that in ſhewing as well theſe Tyrants as the poor people who are forced to live under them, their danger, that is by laying before the former, the helliſh and precipitous courſes they muſt uſe to mantain their power, by repreſenting to the latter; what they muſt ſuffer, I may be inſtrumental, firſt, to deter private Citizens from attempting upon the liberties of their Country, or if they have done it, to make them lay down their ill gotten authority; and then to warn the reſt of the Nobility and people, from theſe factions and malignancies in their ſeveral common-wealths and Governments, which might give hope and opportunity to thoſe who are ambitious amongſt them, to aſpire to an Empire over them. However it prove, I hope I am no more to be blamed for my attempt, then that excellent Phyſician of our Nation is, who hath lately taken ſo much pains to compoſe an excellent Treatiſe, of that foul Diſeaſe which was, not long ſince, brought from the new world into theſe parts; wherein though he be forced to uſe ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as are almoſt able to nauſeate his Readers, and talk of ſuch Ulcers, Boyles, Nodes, Botches, Cankers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that are ſcarce fit to be repeated, eſpecially when he handles the cauſes of thoſe effects, yet he did not intend to teach or exhort men to get this Diſeaſe; much leſs did he bring this lamentable infirmity into the world, but diſcribes it faithfully as it is, to the end men may be bettered, and avoid the being infected with it, and may diſcern and oure it, whenever their incontinence and folly ſhall procure it them. I ſhall ſay no more in this matter; but to conclude all make a proteſtation, that as well in this Book, as in all my other Writing, my only ſcope and deſign is to promote the intereſt and welfare of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and the peace and quiet of the world, both which I am ſo vain as to believe, would be better obtained and provided for, if the principles I lay down were followed and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Princes and people, that they are like to be by thoſe Maxims which are in this Age moſt inavogue. For my ſelf I ſhall only ſay (and call you all to witneſs for the truth of it)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179237:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that as by my Birth I am a Gentleman,<note place="margin">Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note> and of a Family which hath ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many <hi>Gonfaloniers</hi> of Juſtice in it; ſo I have been uſed in many imploy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of great truſt, both in our City and abroad; and at this hour I am not in my Eſtate one penny better for them all, nor ſhould I have been, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though I had never ſuffered any loſſes by the ſeiſure of my Eſtate in the year 1531. for m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carriage it hath ever been void of faction and contention; I never had any prejudice againſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Houſe of <hi>Medici,</hi> but honoured the perſon of all thoſe of that Family whom I knew, and the memory of ſuch of them as lived before me, whom I acknowledge to have been excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Patriots and Pillars of our City and Common-wealth. During the turbulent times of <hi>Piero,</hi> and after his expulſion out of <hi>Florance,</hi> though my employments were but Miniſteral my advice was ask'd in many grave matters, which I ever delivered with impartiality and indifference, not eſpouſing the heady opinions of any, much leſs their paſſions and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities; I never ſided with any Party further than that the Duty of my charge oblieged me to ſerve the prevailing Party, when poſſeſſ'd of the Government of our City; this I ſpeak for thoſe changes that happened between the flight of the ſaid <hi>Piero de Medici,</hi> and the horrid Parricide committed by <hi>Clement</hi> the 7th. upon his indulgent Mother, joyning with his greateſt enemies, and uniting himſelf with thoſe who had uſed the moſt tranſcendent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence to his own perſon, and the higheſt violence and fury the Sun ever ſaw to his poor Courtiers and Subjects, and ſo accompained he might ſheath his Sword in the bowels o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his own deſolate Country. At that time, that during that whole Seige, I muſt confeſs I did break the confines of my Naturality, and not only acted as I was commanded barely but rouz'd my ſelf, and ſtir'd up others haraunging (in the Streets and places of the City the People to defend with the laſt drop of their blood, the Walls of their Country, and the Liberty of their Government; taking very hazardous Journeys to <hi>Ferruccio,</hi> and then into the <hi>Mugello</hi> and other parts, to bring in Succours and Proviſions to our languiſhin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> City, and acting as a Souldier (which was a new profeſſion to me) at the age of above ſixty, when others are deſpenſed from it. For all which, I had ſo entire a ſatisfaction in my mind and conſcience, that I am perſwaded this cordial made me able to ſupport the ſufferings which befell me after our Cataſtrophe, and to rejoice in them ſo far, that all the malice and cruelties of our enemies, could never draw one word from me unſutable to the honour I thought I merited, and did in ſome ſort enjoy, for being inſtrumental to defend (as long as it was poſſible) our Altars and our Hearths. But all that I have undergone hath been abundantly recompenced to me by the favour and courteſie of the moſt excelle<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Signior <hi>Coſimo,</hi> who hath been pleaſed to offer me all the preferments the greateſt ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could aſpire too, which I did not refuſe out of any ſcruple to ſerve ſo incomparable a Prince, whoſe early years manifeſt ſo much Courage, Humanity, and Prudence, and ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly a care of the publick good, but becauſe I was very deſirous not to accept of a charge which I was notable to perform, my years and my infirmities having now brought me to a condition in which I am fitter to live in a Cloyſter than a Palace, and made me good for nothing but to talk of paſt times, the common vice of old Age: So that I did not think it juſt or gratefull to reward this excellent perſon ſo ill for his kindneſs, as to give him a uſeleſs Servant, and to fill up the place of a far better. This is all I think fit to ſay of this matter, I chuſe to addreſs it to you <hi>Zenobio,</hi> for the conſtant friendſhip I have ever enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with you, and formerly with your deceaſed Father, the companion of my Studies, and ornament of our City. And ſo I bid you farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>The firſt of</hi> April, 1537.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
